So, well, I do applied math,
حسناً، أنا أمارس الرياضيات التطبيقية،
and this is a peculiar problem
وهذه مشكلة غريبة
for anyone who does applied math, is that
تواجه أي شخص يمارس الرياضيات التطبيقية وهي
we are like management consultants.
أننا نشبه استشاريي الإدارة.
No one knows what the hell we do.
لا أحد يعلم ما الذي نقوم به.
So I am going to give you some -- attempt today
لذلك سوف أقوم اليوم -- بمحاولة
to try and explain to you what I do.
شرح ما أقوم به لكم.
So, dancing is one of the most human of activities.
حسنا، فالرقص هو أحد النشاطات التي يقوم بها الكثير من البشر.
We delight at ballet virtuosos and tap dancers
نحن سعداء براقصي الباليه الموهوبين وراقصي الرقص النقري
you will see later on.
سوف ترون لاحقاً.
Now, ballet requires an extraordinary level of expertise
الآن، رقص الباليه يتطلب قدراً استثنائياً من الخبرة
and a high level of skill,
ومستوى عاليا من المهارة،
and probably a level of initial suitability
ولرُبما حدا معينا من الملاءمة الأولية
that may well have a genetic component to it.
الذي قد يشتمل على مكوّن وراثي.
Now, sadly, neurological disorders such as Parkinson's disease
والآن، للأسف، فاضطرابات الجهاز العصبي مثل مرض باركنسون
gradually destroy this extraordinary ability,
تدمر تدريجيا هذه الموهبة المتميزة،
as it is doing to my friend Jan Stripling, who was
كما يحدث لصديقي جان ستربلنغ، والذي كان
a virtuoso ballet dancer in his time.
راقص باليه موهوبا جداً في وقته.
So great progress and treatment has been made over the years.
لقد حصل تقدم كبير وتم تركيب العلاج على مر السنين.
However, there are 6.3 million people worldwide
ومع ذلك، هناك 6.3 مليون شخص في جميع أنحاء العالم
who have the disease, and they have to live with
يعانون من هذا المرض، ومفروض عليهم أن يتعايشوا مع
incurable weakness, tremor, rigidity
الضعف غير القابل للعلاج، والرجفة، والتصلب
and the other symptoms that go along with the disease,
والأعراض الأخرى التي تترافق مع هذا المرض
so what we need are objective tools
فما نحتاج إليه هو أدوات موضوعية
to detect the disease before it's too late.
للكشف عن هذا المرض قبل فوات الأوان.
We need to be able to measure progression objectively,
نحن بحاجة إلى أن نكون قادرين على قياس التقدم في المرض موضوعياً
and ultimately, the only way we're going to know
وبشكل عام، السبيل الوحيد الذي سنعلم به
when we actually have a cure is when we have
أنه لدينا علاج حقيقي هو عندما نجد
an objective measure that can answer that for sure.
قياساً موضوعياً قادراً على الإجابة عن ذلك بالتأكيد.
But frustratingly, with Parkinson's disease
لكن بشكل محبط، مع مرض باركنسون
and other movement disorders, there are no biomarkers,
وغيره من اضطرابات الحركة، لا توجد مؤشرات حيوية،
so there's no simple blood test that you can do,
لذلك ليس هناك أي اختبار دم بسيط يمكننا القيام به
and the best that we have is like
وأفضل ما لدينا هو مثل
this 20-minute neurologist test.
هذا الاختبار العصبي الذي يستغرق 20 دقيقة.
You have to go to the clinic to do it. It's very, very costly,
عليك الذهاب إلى العيادة للقيام به. كما أنه مكلفٌ جداً،
and that means that, outside the clinical trials,
وهذا يعني أنه خارج التجارب السريرية
it's just never done. It's never done.
لا يمكن القيام به أبداً. لم يتم ذلك من قبل.
But what if patients could do this test at home?
ولكن ماذا لو استطاع المرضى القيام بهذا الاختبار في المنزل؟
Now, that would actually save on a difficult trip to the clinic,
هذا سيوفّر عليهم فعلاً رحلة صعبة إلى العيادة
and what if patients could do that test themselves, right?
وماذا لو استطاع المرضى القيام بهذا الاختبار بأنفسهم، صحيح؟
No expensive staff time required.
لا داعي لنفقات الموظفين الباهظة الثمن.
Takes about $300, by the way,
بالمناسبة تبلغ تكلفته حوالي 300 دولار،
in the neurologist's clinic to do it.
عند القيام به في عيادة الأعصاب.
So what I want to propose to you as an unconventional way
لهذا ما أريد أن اقترحه عليكم كطريقة غير تقليدية
in which we can try to achieve this,
تمكننا من محاولة تحقيق ذلك
because, you see, in one sense, at least,
لأنه، كما سترون، من جانب واحد، على الأقل
we are all virtuosos like my friend Jan Stripling.
نحن جميعاً موهوبون مثل صديقي جان ستربلنغ.
So here we have a video of the vibrating vocal folds.
هنا لدينا شريط فيديو لحبال صوتية تهتز.
Now, this is healthy and this is somebody making speech sounds,
هذه هي الحالة الصحيحة وهذا شخص يصدر أصواتا أثناء الكلام،
and we can think of ourselves as vocal ballet dancers,
ويمكننا أن نفكر في أنفسنا كراقصي باليه صوتيين،
because we have to coordinate all of these vocal organs
لأنه علينا تنسيق جميع هذه الأعضاء الصوتية
when we make sounds, and we all actually
عندما نصدر أصواتا، ونحن جميعا في الواقع
have the genes for it. FoxP2, for example.
لدينا المورثات اللازمة لذلك. FoxP2، على سبيل المثال.
And like ballet, it takes an extraordinary level of training.
ومثل الباليه، فإنه يتطلب مستوى متميز من التدريب.
I mean, just think how long it takes a child to learn to speak.
أعني، فكروا فقط كم من الوقت يستغرقه طفل ليتعلم الكلام.
From the sound, we can actually track
في الحقيقة يمكننا انطلاقا من الصوت أن نتتبع
the vocal fold position as it vibrates,
موقع الحبال الصوتية عند اهتزازها،
and just as the limbs are affected in Parkinson's,
وكما تتأثر الأطراف في مرض باركنسون
so too are the vocal organs.
تتأثر أيضاً الأعضاء الصوتية.
So on the bottom trace, you can see an example of
وعلى المؤشر السفلي، تستطيعون رؤية مثال على
irregular vocal fold tremor.
اهتزازات صوتية غير منتظمة ومرتعشة.
We see all the same symptoms.
ونرى الأعراض نفسها كاملةً.
We see vocal tremor, weakness and rigidity.
نرى ارتعاشا في الصوت، وضعفا وتصلبا.
The speech actually becomes quieter and more breathy
والكلام يصبح أكثر هدوء وأكثر لهثةً
after a while, and that's one of the example symptoms of it.
وذلك بعد فترة من الوقت، وهذا مثال على الأعراض المرافقة له.
So these vocal effects can actually be quite subtle,
لذلك يمكن لهذه المؤثرات الصوتية أن تكون تكون خفية جداً،
in some cases, but with any digital microphone,
في بعض الحالات، ولكن مع أي ميكروفون رقمي/
and using precision voice analysis software
وباستخدام برنامج لتحليل دقة الصوت
in combination with the latest in machine learning,
في تركيبة من أحدث آلات التعلم،
which is very advanced by now,
والتي هي متقدمة جداً في وقتنا الحاضر
we can now quantify exactly where somebody lies
يمكننا الآن تحديد وبدقة مكان أي شخص
on a continuum between health and disease
بشكل مستمر بين الصحة والمرض
using voice signals alone.
باستخدام الإشارات الصوتية وحدها.
So these voice-based tests, how do they stack up against
إذاً هذه الاختبارات المستندة إلى الصوت، كيف يمكنها الصمود أمام
expert clinical tests? We'll, they're both non-invasive.
الاختبارات السريرية الاختصاصية؟ حسنا، فهي على حد السواء غير غازية.
The neurologist's test is non-invasive. They both use existing infrastructure.
اختبار الأعصاب هو غير غازٍ. كلاهما يستخدم البنية التحتية القائمة.
You don't have to design a whole new set of hospitals to do it.
لسنا مضطرين لتصميم مجموعة جديدة من المستشفيات للقيام بها.
And they're both accurate. Okay, but in addition,
وكلاهما دقيق على حد السواء. حسناً، ولكن بالإضافة إلى ذلك
voice-based tests are non-expert.
الاختبارات المستندة إلى صوت لاتحتاج إلى خبرة.
That means they can be self-administered.
وهذا يعني أنها يمكن أن تجرى بشكل شخصي.
They're high-speed, take about 30 seconds at most.
إنها عالية السرعة، تستغرق حوالي 30 ثانية على الأكثر.
They're ultra-low cost, and we all know what happens.
إنها منخفضة التكلفة للغاية، ونحن جميعا نعرف ما الذي يحدث.
When something becomes ultra-low cost,
عندما يصبح شيء ذي تكلفة منخفضة للغاية
it becomes massively scalable.
فإنه يصبح قابلا للتطوير على نطاق واسع.
So here are some amazing goals that I think we can deal with now.
لذا إليك بعض الأهداف المدهشة التي أعتقد أننا يمكننا التعامل معها الآن.
We can reduce logistical difficulties with patients.
ويمكننا التخفيف من الصعوبات اللوجستيكية التي يتعرض لها المرضى.
No need to go to the clinic for a routine checkup.
لا حاجة للذهاب إلى المستشفى لإجراء الفحوص الروتينية.
We can do high-frequency monitoring to get objective data.
يمكننا القيام برصد عالي التردد للحصول على بيانات موضوعية.
We can perform low-cost mass recruitment for clinical trials,
يمكننا القيام بكميات كبيرة من التوظيفات منخفضة التكلفة للتجارب السريرية،
and we can make population-scale screening
ويمكننا جعل إجراء الفحوصات على نطاق سكاني واسع
feasible for the first time.
ممكناً للمرة الأولى.
We have the opportunity to start to search
ولدينا الفرصة للبدء في البحث
for the early biomarkers of the disease before it's too late.
عن المؤشرات الحيوية المبكرة للمرض قبل أن يتأخر الوقت.
So, taking the first steps towards this today,
لذا، ولاتخاذ الخطوات الأولى نحو هذا اليوم
we're launching the Parkinson's Voice Initiative.
سنقوم بإطلاق مبادرة صوت باركنسون.
With Aculab and PatientsLikeMe, we're aiming
مع Aculab وPatientsLikeMe، هدفنا هو
to record a very large number of voices worldwide
تسجيل عدد كبير جداً من الأصوات في جميع أنحاء العالم
to collect enough data to start to tackle these four goals.
لجمع بيانات كافية للبدء في تحقيق هذه الأهداف الأربعة.
We have local numbers accessible to three quarters
لدينا أرقام محلية متاحة لثلاثة أرباع
of a billion people on the planet.
المليار من الناس على هذا الكوكب.
Anyone healthy or with Parkinson's can call in, cheaply,
أي شخص سليم أو مصاب بمرض الباركنسون يمكنه الاتصال بثمن رخيص،
and leave recordings, a few cents each,
وترك تسجيلات بصوته، بضعة سنتات لكل اتصال،
and I'm really happy to announce that we've already hit
ويسعدني حقاً أن نعلن أننا فعلا قد حققنا
six percent of our target just in eight hours.
ستة في المئة من هدفنا في ثماني ساعات فقط.
Thank you. (Applause)
شكراً لكم. (تصفيق)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Tom Rielly: So Max, by taking all these samples of,
توم رايلي: إذاً ماكس، بأخذ جميع هذه العينات
let's say, 10,000 people,
دعنا نقل، 10 آلاف شخص
you'll be able to tell who's healthy and who's not?
هل تستطيع تحديد الذين يتمتعون بصحة جيدة من المرضى؟
What are you going to get out of those samples?
ما الذي ستسنتجه من هذه العينات؟
Max Little: Yeah. Yeah. So what will happen is that,
ماكس ليتل: نعم. نعم. ما يحدث هو أنه،
during the call you have to indicate whether or not
أثناء الاتصال لديك إشارة إلى ما إذا كانت مصاب بالمرض أم لا
you have the disease or not, you see. TR: Right.
ستشاهد ذلك. توم رايلي: صحيح.
ML: You see, some people may not do it. They may not get through it.
ماكس ليتل: كما ترى، بعض الناس قد لا يقومون بذلك. قد لا يستطعون تحمله.
But we'll get a very large sample of data that is collected
ولكن سوف نحصل على عينة كبيرة جداً من البيانات التي يتم جمعها
from all different circumstances, and it's getting it
من جميع الحالات المختلفة، ونحن نحصل عليها
in different circumstances that matter because then
في حالات مختلفة وهو أمر يعد مهما لأننا آنذاك
we are looking at ironing out the confounding factors,
نستبعد العوامل الملتبسة،
and looking for the actual markers of the disease.
ونقوم بالبحث عن العلامات الحقيقة لهذا المرض.
TR: So you're 86 percent accurate right now?
توم رايلي: إذاً فأنتم الآن دقيقون بنسبة 86 في المئة؟
ML: It's much better than that.
ماكس ليتل: إنه أفضل من ذلك بكثير.
Actually, my student Thanasis, I have to plug him,
في الواقع، طالبي ثانسيس، علي أن أذكره
because he's done some fantastic work,
نظراً لأنه قام بعمل رائع
and now he has proved that it works over the mobile telephone network as well,
والآن قد أثبت أنه يعمل عبر شبكة الهاتف المحمول كذلك
which enables this project, and we're getting 99 percent accuracy.
مما يتيح لهذا المشروع، الحصول على دقة 99 في المئة.
TR: Ninety-nine. Well, that's an improvement.
توم رايلي: تسعة وتسعين. حسنا، هذا تحسنٌ كبير.
So what that means is that people will be able to —
ما يعنيه ذلك هو أن الناس سوف يكونون قادرين على —
ML: (Laughs)
ماكس ليتل: (يضحك)
TR: People will be able to call in from their mobile phones
توم رايلي: الناس سوف يكونون قادرين على الاتصال من هواتفهم النقالة
and do this test, and people with Parkinson's could call in,
والقيام بهذا الاختبار، ويمكن لمرضى باركنسون الاتصال
record their voice, and then their doctor can check up
وتسجيل أصواتهم ومن ثم يمكن للطبيب النظر
on their progress, see where they're doing in this course of the disease.
فيما أحرزوه من تقدم، والنظر في أي مرحلة هم على خط المرض.
ML: Absolutely.
ماكس ليتل: بكل تأكيد.
TR: Thanks so much. Max Little, everybody.
توم رايلي: شكراً جزيلاً. إنه ماكس ليتل يا ناس.
ML: Thanks, Tom. (Applause)
ماكس ليتل: شكراً توم. (تصفيق)